<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Theology Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T16:23:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stephen Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Did the Bible Borrow the Flood Story From the Epic of Gilgamesh?]]></title>
    <link href="http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/did-the-bible-borrow-the-flood-story-from-the-epic-of-gilgamesh/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T21:20:57-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/did-the-bible-borrow-the-flood-story-from-the-epic-of-gilgamesh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 1872 a man by the name of George Smith was sifting through a collection of un-translated cuneiform tablets sitting in a British museum and discovered an ancient Babylonian story that would wind up making history. That story was The Epic of Gilgamesh. While the author of the Epic is unknown, the story itself contains a piece of history that many of us are very familiar with: the historical account of the Noahic Flood that is recorded in the Book of Genesis, the first book of the Holy Bible. At first glance, this might seem like a wonderful archeological discovery that would confirm biblical history, but if we take a closer look we will see that it raises some serious questions about the origin of the flood account within the Book of Genesis. <!--more--></p>

<p>The similarities between the two accounts are too numerous to simply be coincidence. For example, both accounts share the story of an angry god who decides to wipe out all of life from the earth. Both accounts have a man who is spared from the flood in a boat. Both accounts also have these men taking their families on board as well as many animals so that they too can be spared from the flood. Both boats settled on top of a mountain. Both accounts have a raven and a dove that were sent out to see if the waters had subsided, and both men made a sacrifice to a god after they got off the boat. It is quite apparent that both of these stories are being affected by the same influence, but which one came first, the Bible or the Epic?</p>

<p>It is well known that Moses is the man that God chose to record the early history of the world. He is credited for writing the first five books of the Bible known as the Pentateuch. The flood account is found in the first book of the Bible called Genesis which Moses would have written sometime around 1500 BC. On the other hand, the story of The Epic of Gilgamesh is believed to have been in existence sometime around 2500 BC to 2000 BC.  So the question arises, did the Bible take the story from the Epic, or is there some other logical explanation for the amazing similarities?
How Do We Know How Old the Epic Is?</p>

<p>As we have mentioned before, it is believed that The Epic of Gilgamesh was handed down from approximately 2500BC &ndash; 2000 BC. The exact date that this story came into existence and the authorship is unknown. The reason that it is believed that this story originated around that time is because of an ancient clay prism known as the Sumerian Kings List. On this list we have the names of all the kings that ruled in Sumeria, both before and after the flood. There are fifteen known lists of the kings in existence. Interestingly enough, one of the pre-flood kings listed is Gilgamesh. However, can these lists of the kings be trusted? After all, none of these clay lists are in agreement with one another. In their book Lost Treasures of the Bible, Professor Emeritus of Religious Studies, Clyde E. Fant and Professor of Religious Studies, Mitchell G. Reddish state,</p>

<p>Some of the copies of the Sumerian King List do not contain the list of the pre-flood kings. This portion of the list is usually considered to be a secondary addition and may have originated from a different source….The various copies of the Sumerian King List not only differ in whether or not they contain the pre-flood kings, but also in the order of the dynasties, the lengths of the reigns of certain kings, the names of the kings, and the number of the kings.</p>

<p>In describing the Sumerian King Lists they go on to mention that “the length of the reign of each king is given, which in many cases is unrealistically long. The reigns of the pre-flood kings range from 36,000 years to 18,600 years, whereas the post-flood reigns are much lower, ranging from 1500 years to 2 years.” It is these lists of kings that are used to determine that Gilgamesh and the story originated sometime around 2500 BC &ndash; 2000 BC. However, with all the unrealistic life spans and the discrepancies of the times that the kings ruled, can these lists of the kings be trusted to date the ancient Babylonian dynasties with any accuracy? If this were a court of law the evidence would be thrown out because of the lack of harmony and blatant inconsistencies, and the date of the Epic would remain an unanswered archeological mystery.</p>

<p>Where Did the Epic Come From?</p>

<p>In his book The Gilgamesh Epic and Old Testament Parallels, Alexander Heidel, an expert in Semitics and ancient Near Eastern history, has observed that the Epic is actually a collection of previously “unrelated sources” that were “put together” to make one large epic story. That is to say that the Epic as we know it today is far more complex than it used to be. The Epic itself has evolved over the many centuries that have gone by, being added to by each passing generation. As a matter of fact, the flood story may not have even been a part of the original stories of Gilgamesh. It is believed that it was inserted at a much later date. An excellent book on this topic is The Evolution of the Gilgamesh Epic written by Jeffrey H. Tigay, the Associate Professor of Hebrew and Semitic Languages and Literatures in the Department of Oriental Studies at the University of Pennsylvania. After listing several good evidences to support his claim he comes to the conclusion that the flood story in the Epic of Gilgamesh was taken from another epic known as the Atra-hasis Epic. According to Tigay, the source of the flood material that is mentioned in much ancient Babylonian literature is found in the Atra-hasis Epic. So what do we know about the Atra-hasis Epic? Fant and Reddish record that,</p>

<p>The best preserved edition of the Epic of Atrahasis comes from the Old Babylonian period, written around 1635 B.C.E. This version of the tale was written on three tablets, with a total of approximately 1245 lines of text. These tablets can be dated rather precisely because each tablet bears the name of the scribe who wrote it (Ku-Aya) and the time of its composition during the reign of the Babylonian king Ammisaduqa.
It very interesting to note that the flood story as it is found in the Atra-hasis Epic does not contain all the similarities that we find with The Epic of Gilgamesh and the Bible.</p>

<p>The best preserved and most complete version of the Epic of Gilgamesh was the one that was discovered in the library of the last great Babylonian king, Ashurbanipal, who reigned from 685 BC to 627 BC. These were the tablets that George Smith translated. By the time that Moses wrote the Book of Genesis in 1500 BC, until the time of Ashurbanipal in 685 BC, there would have been over 800 years of the telling of the story of the Epic of Gilgamesh. This would have provided ample time for the Epic to gain the similarities of the historical flood account found in the Book of Genesis.</p>

<p>E.A. Wallis Budge from the Department of Egyptian and Assyrian Antiquities quotes Ashurbanipal as saying, “I, Ashur-bani-pal, within it understood the wisdom of Nebo, all the art of writing of every craftsman, of every kind, I made myself master of them all.” From this, Budge deduces that Ashurbanipal was an expert in cuneiform text, which is what the Epic at his library was written in. He believes that Ashurbanipal went to great lengths to create a library of all the history of his people and that the Epic that was discovered in his library might very well have been revised by Ashurbanipal himself.</p>

<p>Are There Other Flood Stories</p>

<p>The question may come to mind that if there are ancient and varying versions of the flood story in ancient Mesopotamia, are there any others in the world? The answer is, yes. There are hundreds of ancient versions of flood stories from around the world. Some are close to what we find in the Bible while others are not. There are about twenty that have many similarities that we find in the Bible. They range anywhere from Ancient Babylon and Hawaii, all the way down to Australia and many places in between.</p>

<p>But where did all these stories of the flood come from? We know from the Bible that God created the heavens and the earth and all that is in them and that everything God made was good, including Adam and Eve. God gave Adam and Eve only one rule, and that was to not eat from tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil. They chose to disobey God. God cast them out of the garden and sin and death entered the world as a result of their choice. They had children and their children’s children had more children. It was not long before mankind and sin were rampant. God was grieved at this and decided to destroy all life from the face of the earth, but He chose to spare His faithful servant, Noah. God flooded the world until the waters covered the highest mountains and all was destroyed except Noah and his three sons, their wives, and all the animals that were on board the ark.</p>

<p>It is interesting to note here that according to James Ussher’s The Annals of the World, the date that is given to when the flood may have occurred was 2349 BC. If that date sounds familiar, it is because it is the same time frame that is believed to be the origin of the flood story found in the Epic of Gilgamesh. It is also interesting to note that beyond the time of the flood, the history is no longer reliable on the list of the Babylonian kings. If the flood story were true as we find it in the Book of Genesis, we would expect that to be the case. The only accurate history would have been the history from Noah and his family that was passed on.</p>

<p>After the flood, God promised that He would no longer destroy the world by means of another global flood. Noah and his family settled into the world and had children, and his children’s children had more children. Once again the world was populated. But this time the Bible tells us that they were consolidated to one area. They were prideful people and wanted to make a name for themselves, so they started to build a tower that would reach the heavens. We know this historical account as the Tower of Babel. Interestingly enough, the location of the tower was in Ancient Mesopotamia. It was not God’s will that the people stay in one area and elevate themselves, so God confused them by giving them different languages. As a result of this the building of the tower stopped, and the people dispersed throughout the world with each group of people taking with them the account of the flood. As would be expected, over the years the story would be tailored to the cultural differences of the people telling the story. As a result of this event, we would expect to find numerous flood stories from around the world.</p>

<p>Conclusion</p>

<p>There are three schools of thought about the flood story in the Bible in relation to the flood story in the Epic of Gilgamesh. According to Heidel, they are, “First, the Babylonians borrowed from the Hebrew account; second, the Hebrew account is dependent on the Babylonian; third, both are descended from a common original.” Out of these three accounts, an intelligent argument can be made for each. Those who do not wish to acknowledge God will adopt the second school of thought, but history, when understood from a proper perspective, favors a healthy combination of the first and third school of thought. Both accounts of the flood are records of an actual historical even that took place over 4,000 years ago, and the similarities in the accounts were not fully emulated until after the writing of the Book of Genesis. That is to say that the similarities in the Epic of Gilgamesh are dependent on the Bible. While it may be true that the Epic has evolved over the last few millennia, our God is the same yesterday, today, and tomorrow, and so is His Word. The Bible continues to withstand the test of time and proves itself to be historically accurate time and time again.</p>

<p>By: Stephen Lee</p>

<p>Bibliography
Ahmed, Sami Said. Sothern Mesopotamia in the Time of Ashurbanipal. Netherlands: Mouton &amp; Co., 1968.</p>

<p>Budge, E. A. Wallis, The Babylonian Story of the Deluge and the Epic of Gilgamish (1929)</p>

<pre><code>  http://www.sacred-texts.com/ane/gilgdelu.htm (Accessed April 26, 2013)
</code></pre>

<p>Fant, Clyde E., and Mitchell G. Reddish. Lost Treasures of the Bible: Understanding the Bible through Archaeological Artifacts in World Museums. Grand Rapids: Wm. B. Eerdmans, 2008.</p>

<p>Heidel, Alexander. The Gilgamesh Epic and Old Testament Parallels. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. 1946.</p>

<p>Kriwaczek, Paul. Babylon: Mesopotamia and the Birthplace of Civilization. New York: St. Martens Press. 2010.</p>

<p>Smith, George. “The Gilgamesh Epic is Found.” In Hands on the Past: Pioneer Archaeologists Tell Their Own Story. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1966.
Tigay, Jeffrey H. The Evolution of the Gilgamesh Epic. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press. 1982.</p>

<p>White, A. J.  Monty. “Flood Legends.” In Answers. Vol. 2 No. 2 (2007)</p>

<p>Pierce, Larry and Marion. James Usher’s: The Annals of the World. Forest: Master Books. 2004.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Did God Divorce the Nation of Israel?]]></title>
    <link href="http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/did-god-divorce-the-nation-of-israel/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T20:03:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://Lee-Stephen.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/did-god-divorce-the-nation-of-israel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are some who have laid claim that God divorced the nation of Israel. They even teach it as a biblical truth. Not just any old divorce, mind you, but a divorce as we understand it today between a husband and wife whose marriage has withered to the point of a corrosive decay. Eventually they part their separate ways to find a new life on their own again. While there is a great deal of biblical evidence to indicate that there was definitely a separation that took place between God and the nation of Israel, it was not what we understand to be a divorce by the commonly accepted definition today.<!--more--></p>

<p>The book of Hosea tells us the historical account of the relationship between God and Israel through the life of a prophet whose name was Hosea. God told Hosea, “Go and marry a promiscuous wife and have children of promiscuity, for the whole land has been promiscuous by abandoning the LORD.” (Hosea 1:2b HCSB) This relationship that Hosea would have with his wife would serve as a living allegory of God’s love and patience with the nation of Israel. Thomas Edward McComiskey describes Hosea’s marriage as, “…one of the most remarkable depictions of divine grace in the Old Testament.”1</p>

<p>Hosea did exactly as God had called him to do. He married a woman named Gomer and they had children together. There is some debate as to whether or not all of the children that Gomer had were actually Hosea’s, but that is another discussion for another day.</p>

<p>The difficulty for Hosea and his marriage with Gomer was the simple fact that his wife was promiscuous indeed. While she may have accepted Hosea’s marriage proposal and entered into a covenant relationship with him, she still longed for freedom from Hosea to do as she pleased, when she pleased. I do not doubt that Gomer loved her husband, but she loved herself and her own selfish desires even more. How do we know this to be true of Gomer? We must remember that the marriage between Gomer and Hosea was a picture of God’s covenant relationship with the nation of Israel; therefore, if we look at the nation of Israel, we also get a picture of what Gomer was like.</p>

<p>What was the nation of Israel like during the time of Hosea? God describes them as being promiscuous and having abandoned Him. Hosea says:
“Hear the word of the LORD, people of Israel, for the LORD has a case against the inhabitants of the land: There is no truth, no faithful love, and no knowledge of God in the land! Cursing, lying, murder, stealing, and adultery are rampant; one act of bloodshed follows another.” (Hosea 4:1-2 HCSB)
God continues to plea His case before the nation of Israel through Hosea by saying:
“My people consult their wooden idols, and their divining rods inform them. For a spirit of promiscuity leads them astray; they act promiscuously in disobedience to their God. They sacrifice on the mountaintops, and they burn offerings on the hills, and under the oaks, poplars, and terebinths, because their shade is pleasant. And so your daughters act promiscuously and your daughters-in-law commit adultery.” (Hosea 4:12-13 HCSB)</p>

<p>Indeed, this was a time of great promiscuity for the nation of Israel. Like Gomer, they entered into a covenant with God to be wholly devoted to Him, but they also longed to please themselves by pursuing their own lustful desires whenever and wherever they wished.</p>

<p>Now that we have an understanding of what the nation of Israel was like, we have a better understanding of what Gomer was like. I believe she, like the nation of Israel,   was guilty of lying, cursing, stealing, worshipping false gods, and yes, possibly even bloodshed. What an embarrassment she must have been to Hosea. In the same way, what an embarrassment the nation of Israel must have been for God. Matthew Henry puts it this way:
“What an odious thing would it be for the prophet, a holy man, to have a whorish wife, and children whorish like her! What an exercise would it be of his patience, and, if she persisted in it, what could be expected but that he should give her a bill of divorce! And is it not then much more offensive to the holy God to have such a people as this to be called by his name and have a place in his house?”</p>

<p>If there was anyone who had a just cause to divorce his wife, it was Hosea. If there was any god who had just cause to divorce his people, it was Israel’s God. But that is not what we see. We see a withdrawal instead. How is this different from what we understand to be a divorce today? The difference is in the covenant that was made between God and His people.</p>

<p>First, God’s covenant that He made with Abraham (which was both literal and spiritual) was conditional, but it only called for circumcision as an act of obedience in order for that covenant to continue (Genesis 17:9-14).</p>

<p>The Abrahamic Covenant was later modified after God led the descendents of Abraham out of Egypt (Exodus 19-24).  This was called the Mosaic Covenant and its condition was obedience to the law. The Mosaic Covenant states:
“Now if you listen to Me and carefully keep My covenant, you will be My own possession out of all the peoples, although all the earth is Mine, and you will be My kingdom of priests and My holy nation. These are the words that you are to say to the Israelites.” (Exodus 19:5-6 HCSB)
Dr. Wayne Grudem says this in regards to the Mosaic Covenant:
“…the Mosaic covenant itself, with all of its detailed laws, could not save people. It is not that the laws were wrong in themselves, for they were given by a holy God, but they had no power to give people new life, and the people were not able to obey them perfectly…”</p>

<p>The Apostle Peter says, in regards to the law, “Why then are you testing God by putting on a yoke that neither our forefathers nor we have been able to bear?” (Acts 15:10 HCSB) Clearly the Mosaic Covenant was not a covenant that Israel was able to live up to, and is the covenant that the nation of Israel was found guilty of breaking.</p>

<p>Second, we need to understand that The Mosaic Covenant did not nullify the Abrahamic Covenant. Paul says, “And I say this: the law, which came 430 years later, does not revoke a covenant that was previously ratified by God, so as to cancel a promise.” (Galatians 3:17 HCSB)</p>

<p>Third, God lived up to His covenant promise by remaining Israel’s God. Did He punish them? Absolutely! This punishment consisted of a withdrawal (Hosea 2:6-13) from the nation of Israel as a result of their not keeping the Mosaic Covenant. It was not a complete disowning, as many understand it today. To completely disown the nation of Israel would be to go back on His promise to Abraham and to deny His own Seed.  Paul identifies this seed as Jesus Christ.
“Now the promises were spoken to Abraham and to his seed. He does not say ‘and to seeds,’ as though referring to many, but and to your seed, referring to one, who is Christ.” (Galatians 3:16 HCSB)</p>

<p>“For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ have put on Christ. There is no Jew or Greek, slave or free, male or female; for you are all one in Christ Jesus. And if you are Christ’s, then you are Abraham’s seed, heirs according to the promise.” (Galatians 3:27-29 HCSB)</p>

<p>Fourth, Isaiah questions the existence of a certificate of divorce which would indicate that the covenant had indeed been abolished. It says:
“This is what the LORD says: Where is your mother’s divorce certificate that I used to send her away? Or who were My creditors that I sold you to? Look, you were sold for your iniquities, and your mother was put away because of your transgressions.” (Isaiah 50:1 HCSB)
The implication in Isaiah is that the reason the relationship was broken was because of Israel’s departure from God, not God’s departure from Israel. Thomas Edward McComiskey puts it this way in his commentary on Hosea:
“…‘for she is not my wife, and I am not her husband.’ The suggestion that these words represent a legal divorce formula in this passage is questionable. The view is based on Akkadian and Elephantine sources, and while it may reflect later Jewish practice with regard to divorce, it is not consonant with this context. The point is not that Yahweh has declared his relationship with Israel severed because he wants it to be so, but that the relationship has been severed by Israel’s wantonness and Yahweh wants it restored. This is why he pleads with his errant wife. The passage is best understood against the background of another prophetic tradition which depicts Yahweh as saying that the severance of his relationship with Israel was not a result of divorce, for no bill of divorce existed, but it was the result if Israel’s transgression (Isa. 50:1). Israel had removed herself from her covenant obligation and from her covenant relationship to God as well.”</p>

<p>Fifth, we again need to remember that Hosea’s marriage represented God’s relationship with the nation of Israel. Just as Hosea never divorced his wife, God could not have divorced the nation of Israel. How can we be sure that Hosea never divorced his wife? We can be sure because if he had divorced her he would have been going against the Mosaic Law by taking her back. The Law says:
“If a man marries a woman, but she becomes displeasing to him because he finds something improper about her, he may write her a divorce certificate, hand it to her, and send her away from his house. If after leaving his house she goes and becomes another man’s wife, and the second man hates her, writes her a divorce certificate, hands it to her, and sends her away from his house or if he dies, the first husband who sent her away may not marry her again after she has been defiled, because that would be detestable to the LORD.” (Deuteronomy 24:1-4a HCSB)</p>

<p>If Hosea had divorced his wife, he would not have been able to take her back. Yet we see him buying her back (Hosea 3:1-2). So if God had divorced Israel, then Hosea’s marriage to Gomer would no longer accurately depict God’s relationship with Israel.</p>

<p>Hosea, after his wife leaves him, ultimately buys his wife back. He did this in obedience to God’s command to. “…Go, show your love to your wife again, though she is loved by another and is an adulteress. Love her as the LORD loves the Israelites, though they turn to other gods and love the sacred raisin cakes.’” (Hosea 3:1 NIV)  Despite all that Gomer had done to Hosea, he still demonstrated an act of love to her by buying her back. Now, not only did she need to be faithful to Hosea under the laws of marriage, but also by rights of Hosea having purchased her as a slave. Similarly, God ultimately buys back the nation of Israel through the shed blood of Jesus Christ on the cross.</p>

<p>Hosea said to Gomer, “You must live with me many days. Don’t be promiscuous or belong to any man, and I will act the same way toward you.” (Hosea 3:3 HCSB) This explains the present state of Israel, because God also said through Hosea to the nation of Israel, “For the Israelites must live many days without king or prince, without sacrifice or sacred pillar, and without ephod or household idols.” (Hosea 3:4 HCSB)</p>

<p>In closing, the nation of Israel can look forward to again receiving the full blessing that was promised them by way of the Abrahamic Covenant, but not until God’s time. Until then, they must live as described by Hosea in Hosea 3:3. The Apostle Paul sheds a great deal of light on all that has taken place with the nation of Israel in the eleventh chapter of the book of Romans. He also confirms God’s promise by saying,“So that you will not be conceited, brothers, I do not want you to be unaware of this mystery: a partial hardening has come to Israel until the full number of the Gentiles has come in. And in this way all Israel will be saved, as it is written: The liberator will come from Zion; He will turn away godlessness from Jacob. And this will be My covenant with them, when I take away their sins. Regarding the gospel, they are enemies for your advantage, but regarding election, they are loved because of their forefathers, since God’s gracious gifts and calling are irrevocable.” (Romans 11:25-29 HCSB)</p>

<p>Thomas E. McComiskey says,“..we must understand the words not my people to apply only to the status of the people of Hosea’s day. The promise is eternal (Gen. 13:15; 17:7-8, 13, 19; 48:4). God affirms that though he may forsake a disobedient generation (Lev. 26:33), he will not vitiate his promise: ‘Yet for all that, … when they are in the land of their enemies … I will remember in their favor the covenant with their ancestors … to be their God.’ (Lev. 26:44-45 NRSV).”</p>

<p>No, God did not divorce the nation of Israel, but as the Scriptures show, God has only temporarily withdrawn Himself from them. A time is coming when once again God will renew His vows with her and He will say, “I will take you to be my wife forever. I will take you to be My wife in righteousness, justice, love, and compassion. I will take you to be My wife in faithfulness, and you will know the LORD.” (Hosea 2:19-20 HCSB)</p>

<pre><code>    By: Stephen Lee
</code></pre>

<p>1 The Minor Prophets: An Exegetical &amp; Expository Commentary, By Thomas E. McComiskey, Baker Book House Company, c1992.</p>

<p>2 Henry, M. 1996, c1991. Matthew Henry&rsquo;s commentary on the whole Bible: Complete and unabridged in one volume. Hendrickson: Peabody</p>

<p>3 Systematic Theology, By Wayne Grudem, Inter-Varsity Press &amp; Zondervan Publishing House, c1994</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
